<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
 xml:id="cha.slepos_wireless">
 <title>Wireless Setup and Rollout</title>
 <info/>
 <para>
  <!--Since SLEPOS11 SP2 FP1 --> It is possible to use wireless networks
  (Wi-Fi) to connect wireless &slepos; terminals. The wireless support must
  be added when building images. The wireless support is included only in
  the netboot image &ndash; PXE booting via wireless networks is however
  not supported. The first boot of the wireless can be performed using a
  preloaded image or an image on a USB stick. It is also possible to use a
  temporary LAN connection. </para>
 <para> A typical scenario: </para>
 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para> The terminal boots locally from a USB stick or a preloaded image.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para> The wireless adapter is configured and connects to the predefined
    access point. </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para> The appropriate image is downloaded from the &branchserv; and
    installed. </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <note>
  <title>Multiple Network Interfaces</title>
  <para> If a terminal uses multiple network interfaces (LAN and wireless,
   for example), a new record in LDAP and new
    <filename>config.MAC</filename> is created for each interface. All
   interfaces have the same hostname and IP address assigned by DHCP.
  </para>
 </note>
 <sect1>
  <title>Service Partition</title>
  <para> For the wireless operation of &slepos; terminals, a service
   partition on each terminal's hard drive is needed for storing the netboot
   kernel and initrd. The service partition must be the first partition on
   the terminal's hard drive and mounted as
    <filename>/srv/SLEPOS</filename>. </para>
  <para> To create the service partition, use the
    <systemitem>scPartition</systemitem> object with
    <systemitem>scPartNum</systemitem>
   <literal>0</literal>, <systemitem>scPartType</systemitem>
   <literal>83</literal> and <systemitem>scPartMount</systemitem>
   <literal>/srv/SLEPOS</literal>. For more information about creating the
   partition setup, see <xref linkend="sec.slepos_term.ldap.harddisk"/>. </para>
  <para> The minimum size of the service partition sufficient for the
   wireless operation is 200 MB. However, the service partition is also
   used for downloading compressed images with multicast option and will be
   used for other purposes in the future. The recommended size of the
   service partition is 20 GB. </para>
  <para>
   <!--bnc831399--> If booting from the service partition is required (for
   example when wireless operation or offline deployment is used),
    <systemitem>grub</systemitem> must be included in
    <systemitem>initrd</systemitem>. This can be accomplished by adding
    <literal>&lt;package name="grub" bootinclude="true"/&gt;</literal> (or <literal>&lt;package name="grub2" bootinclude="true"/&gt;</literal> for &slepos; 12) to
   the <filename>config.xml</filename> file or by adding
    <systemitem>grub</systemitem> to the list of packages to include in
   boot in via &imgcreat;. </para>
  <para> The service partition cannot be encrypted. </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <!--ok-->
  <title>Creating Images for Wireless Setup</title>
  <para> Boot images used for the wireless setup must have wireless setup
   enabled. The following lines must be present in the
    <filename>config.xml</filename> file, in the <literal>&lt;packages
    type="image"...&lt;</literal> section: </para>
  <screen>
&lt;!-- begin wireless support --&gt;
                &lt;package name="kernel-firmware" bootinclude="true"/&gt;
                &lt;package name="wpa_supplicant" bootinclude="true"/&gt;
                &lt;package name="wireless-tools" bootinclude="true"/&gt;
                &lt;package name="libnl" bootinclude="true"/&gt;
                &lt;package name="grub" bootinclude="true"/&gt;
                &lt;archive name="wlan.tar.gz" bootinclude="true"/&gt;
&lt;!-- end wireless support --&gt;
</screen>
  <para> Also, the wireless drivers must be enabled in the drivers section
   of the <filename>config.xml</filename> file: </para>
  <screen>
&lt;!-- begin wireless support --&gt;
        &lt;drivers type="drivers"&gt;
                &lt;file name="drivers/net/wireless/*"/&gt;
                &lt;file name="drivers/net/wireless/*/*"/&gt;
        &lt;/drivers&gt;
&lt;!-- end wireless support --&gt;
</screen>
  <para> The necessary lines are already present in the provided
   configuration of the minimal image, but they are commented out. The
   wireless configuration is contained in the
    <filename>/etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf</filename> file
   present in the <filename>wlan.tar.gz</filename> tarball and can be
   adjusted there. </para>
  <para> To create the initial boot image with &kiwi;, use the
    <command>kiwi --bootusb</command>
   <replaceable>initrd</replaceable> command. The image must be of the
   netboot type. The <replaceable>initrd</replaceable> must be an initrd
   file with wireless support enabled in the
    <filename>config.xml</filename> file. The kernel is expected to be in
   the same directory and follow the same naming convention. For example: </para>
  <screen>
 cd /var/lib/SLEPOS/system/images/<replaceable>minimal-3.4.0</replaceable>
 kiwi --bootusb <replaceable>initrd-netboot-suse-SLES11.i686-2.1.1.splash.gz</replaceable>
</screen>
  <para> The resulting image can be used for booting from an USB stick or
   it can be preloaded on the hard drive. </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <!--ok-->
  <title>Multicast Over Wireless Networks</title>
  <para> Most current Wi-Fi networks do not support multicast correctly and
   switch to the lowest available network speed when multicast TFTP is
   used. Unless you are using accesspoints supporting high speed multicast
   over Wi-Fi, it is recommended to use FTP instead of multicast TFTP on
   such networks. </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="multipleinterfaces">
  <!--ok-->
  <title>Using a Terminal with Multiple Network Interfaces</title>
  <para> &slepos; supports terminals having more than one network interface
   (for example WiFi and LAN or more than one LAN). During registration and
   subsequent boots, the list of all interfaces is retrieved and LDAP
   updated (attribute <systemitem>macAddress</systemitem> of the
    <systemitem>scWorkstation object</systemitem>). This ensures that
    <filename>config.MAC</filename> files, MAC directories and specific pxe
   files are correctly created (or linked) for all interfaces, so the
   machine can freely use any of then to boot. </para>
  <para> MAC interfaces cannot be directly interchanged between
   workstations, because the workstation is identified by them. To
   accomplish this, a two step procedure is needed: the MAC(s) of the
   interface(s) to be exchanged must first be deregistred, by removing the
   interface(s) from the machine(s) and rebooting the machine(s). The
    <command>posleases2ldap</command> script then removes the MAC(s) from
   the workstation's LDAP data. After that, they can be reused, so the
   interface(s) can be moved into another machine(s). </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
