<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.slepos_imgcreator">
 <title>Building Images with the &imgcreat; Tool</title>

 <para>
  &imgcreat;, the recommended graphical front-end to build images, can be
  started from &yast; by choosing <menuchoice>
  <guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu> <guimenu>&imgcreat;</guimenu>
  </menuchoice>.
  <remark>No need to repeat everything already said in the previous para (file slepos_imagebuilding.xml).</remark>
 </para>

 <para>
  When &imgcreat; is started, the &imgcreat; Configuration Overview
  dialog is shown. It lists image configurations saved in the
  <filename>/var/lib/SLEPOS/system</filename> directory. You can add, delete,
  or edit configurations by using the appropriate buttons in the dialog. Images
  can be built from a newly added configuration or from a configuration opened
  by <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
 </para>

 <figure xml:id="fig.imagecreator">
  <title>The &imgcreat; Configuration Overview</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="imagecreator-overview.png" width="95%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="imagecreator-overview.png" width="95%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>

 <note>
  <title>Login in as &rootuser; User</title>
  <para>
   To be able to log in as &rootuser; on the terminal, you need to
   create the &rootuser; user and assign a password to it in the
   <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab.
  </para>
 </note>

 <note>
  <title>Creating Images from Scratch</title>
  <para>
   Only image templates shipped with &slepos; are supported. If you want to
   prepare your own image from scratch, the &sle; 11 Software Development Kit (SLE-11-SDK) product must be used and
   the <systemitem>kiwi-desc-*</systemitem> packages installed. There is no L3
   support available for the SLE-11-SDK product.
  </para>
 </note>

 <important>
  <title>Building 32-bit Images on 64-bit Machines</title>
  <para>
   Terminals based on &slepos; 11 need 32-bit images. If you want to build 32-bit images on a
   64-bit machine, the Subscription Management Tool (SMT) must be used for
   repository management. It is also recommended to use SMT for &sle; update
   repositories (SLES-11-Updates, SLE-11-POS-Updates). For SMT configuration,
   see &smtguide;.
  </para>
  <para>
   If SMT is configured, add repositories in &imgcreat;. Click <menuchoice>
   <guimenu>Add</guimenu> <guimenu>Specify URL</guimenu> </menuchoice> and
   enter the repository URL, for example:
   <literal>http://smt.mycompany.us/repo/$RCE/SLES11-Updates/sle-11-i586/</literal>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <command>linux32 kiwi</command> command needs to be used when building
   32-bit images on 64-bit machines.
  </para>
 </important>

 <sect2 xml:id="imagecreator.images">
  <title>Creating an Image Based on Templates</title>
  <para>
   To create a new image configuration from a template shipped with &slepos;
   follow these steps:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu>
     <guimenu>&imgcreat;</guimenu></menuchoice> in the &yast; control
     center.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the &imgcreat; Configuration Overview dialog, click
     <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. The <guimenu>Image Preparation</guimenu> dialog
     appears.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the name of the new configuration in the <guimenu>&kiwi;
     Configuration</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <guimenu>Base on Template</guimenu> and choose the template to use
     from the list. If you want to re-use a previously created configuration,
     select <guimenu>Base on Existing Configuration</guimenu> and choose the
     directory with the configuration to use.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>Image Type</guimenu> you want to create. To create a
     bootable live CD with a system image, choose <guimenu>Live ISO
     Image</guimenu>. To create a bootable USB flash drive with a system image,
     choose <guimenu>USB Stick Image</guimenu>. If you need to boot clients
     from the network using PXE/DHCP and then download a system image from the
     network, select <guimenu>Network Boot Image</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The path in which the directory with the image will be created is set in
     the <guimenu>Output Directory</guimenu>. The default value is determined
     by the template and you can leave it as it is.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Package repositories used for creating the image are listed in the
     <guimenu>Package Repository</guimenu> table. The templates include paths
     to copies of the &sle; Server and &slepos; source media located in
     the default distribution directory
     <filename>/var/lib/SLEPOS/dist/</filename>.
<!--These copies should be
     created using POSCopyTool before creating images. For more information
     about these tools, see
     <xref linkend="cha.slepos_postool"
      xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>.-->
    </para>
    <para>
     To add a new repository, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>, select the type of
     the repository and enter the required information. If the image building
     server is on the same architecture as the terminals (i586), it is possible
     to use update repositories defined in the operating system. To add a
     system repository, configure the update repository according to the SLES
     &admin; and use <guimenu>Add From System</guimenu> in &imgcreat;.
    </para>
    <para>
     It is also possible to manually add selected packages to the
     <filename>/var/lib/SLEPOS/system/<replaceable>image_name</replaceable>/repo/</filename>
     directory.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Next</guimenu> to proceed with creating the image
     configuration. &imgcreat; now downloads the repository metadata. This
     action may take some time. If the configured repositories are not valid,
     &imgcreat; will report that.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the Image Configuration dialog, add <literal>root</literal> and other
     needed users. Otherwise, you can use the default values defined in the
     template. To edit the settings, see
     <xref linkend="imagecreator.imageconfig"/>. Click
     <guimenu>Finish</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You are asked if the image should be created now. To create the image,
     select <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>. If you choose <guimenu>No</guimenu>, the
     image configuration will be saved but no image will be built.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     A window showing logs opens. After successfully creating the image, click
     <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The path to the directory containing the new image
     is shown. Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2>
  <title>Building Network Boot Images</title>
  <para>
   In environments where the available network infrastructure is suitable to
   boot &slepos; terminals over LAN, you can use network boot images and
   boot clients using PXE/DHCP. Network boot images are built together with any
   system image when the <guimenu>Network Boot Image</guimenu> option in
   &imgcreat; is selected. If you want to create a system image with a
   network boot image using &imgcreat;, follow these steps:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &imgcreat; and create an image as described in
     <xref linkend="imagecreator.images" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>. Select
     <guimenu>Network Boot Image</guimenu> as <guimenu>Image Type</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Manually copy all the created files including the MD5 checksum files to
     the <filename>/srv/SLEPOS/boot/</filename> and
     <filename>/srv/SLEPOS/image/</filename> directories on the administration
     server. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="sec.adminserv.bootimagecopying"/> and
     <xref linkend="sec.adminserv.systemimagecopying"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="imagecreator.buildimmage">
  <title>Building Bootable CD Images with a System Image</title>
  <para>
   In environments where no suitable network infrastructure is available to
   boot &slepos; terminals over the LAN, you can use bootable live CDs
   containing system images. To create such images using &imgcreat;, follow
   these steps:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &imgcreat; and create an image as described in
     <xref linkend="imagecreator.images" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>. Select
     <guimenu>Live ISO Image</guimenu> as <guimenu>Image Type</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the image creation is completed, burn the created image to CD using
     any CD burning application, for example Nautilus in GNOME or k3b in KDE.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2>
  <title>Building Bootable CD Images without a System Image</title>
  <para>
   If the terminals are not able to boot from network over the PXE/DHCP but the
   network is present, CDs without a system image can be used to boot the
   client system. The system image is downloaded from the network after the
   boot process.
   <remark>mdejmek: do you mean after rebooting
    here?</remark>
   <remark>after it is booted, not necessarily rebooted, i would keep the
    current wording, it is clear, imho</remark>
   To create such images using &imgcreat;, follow these steps:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start &imgcreat; and create an image as described in
     <xref linkend="imagecreator.images" xrefstyle="SectTitleOnPage"/>. Select
     <guimenu>Network Boot Image</guimenu> as <guimenu>Image Type</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change to the directory containing the created image.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The ISO image should now be created using &kiwi;.
    </para>
    <para>
     <command>kiwi --bootcd</command>
     <replaceable>path_to_the_initrd</replaceable>
    </para>
    <para>
     For example:
    </para>
    <para>
     <command>kiwi --bootcd</command>
     <replaceable>initrd-netboot-suse-SLES11.i686-2.1.1.splash.gz</replaceable>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     After the image creation is completed, burn the created ISO image to CD
     using any CD burning application, for example Nautilus in GNOME or k3b in
     KDE.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="serverimages">
  <title>Building Server Images in &imgcreat;</title>
  <para>
   For building server images (for &admserv;, &branchserv; or
   &combserv;) with &imgcreat;, a 64-bit &imgserv; is necessary. The
   <guimenu>32bit Architecture Image</guimenu> option in &imgcreat; should
   be unchecked when building these images.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="imagecreator.rpmdocu">
  <title>Adding Installable Documentation in RPM Format</title>
  <para>
   To include documentation packages in RPM format in your images, follow this
   procedure:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a new image with &imgcreat;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Finish the image settings and quit the &imgcreat; without building the
     image.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the
     <filename>/var/lib/SLEPOS/system/<replaceable>image_name</replaceable>/config.xml</filename>
     file, remove the line containing
     <literal>&lt;rpm-excludedocs&gt;True&lt;/rpm-excludedocs&gt;</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Return to the &imgcreat;, edit the last image, and start building the
     image.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="imagecreator.imageconfig">
  <title>Image Configuration Settings</title>
  <para>
   <remark>mdejmek: we need an introductory sentence here; for next release!
    TODO</remark>
   In the <guimenu>Image Configuration</guimenu> tab, adjust the configuration
   of the software in the resulting image. In the relevant fields, set the
   <guimenu>Version</guimenu> of the image and its <guimenu>Size</guimenu> in
   the selected <guimenu>Units</guimenu>. If the <guimenu>Additive</guimenu>
   option is active, the value entered in <guimenu>Size</guimenu> is added to
   the size of the selected packages. The set value is the minimal free space
   on the image.
  </para>
  <para>
   To add or remove a pattern or a package from the <guimenu>Installed
   Software</guimenu> list, click <guimenu>Change</guimenu>. Packages in the
   <guimenu>Ignored Software</guimenu> list are removed from any patterns to be
   installed, but they remain installed and are available to be selected as
   individual packages or dependencies. Packages in the <guimenu>Packages to
   Delete</guimenu> list are always uninstalled from the target image without
   any dependency checking. To put packages on a list, click in the list window
   and write the name of the packages with one name per line.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Package Versions and Taboos</title>
   <para>
    &imgcreat; does not support package version selection and it installs
    the newest package version all time. Taboos are also not supported.
   </para>
  </note>
  <note>
   <title>Deleted Dependencies</title>
   <para>
    If you add any package to a template-based image, make sure that it does
    not depend on any packages set to be deleted. Remove these packages with
    dependencies from the <guimenu>Packages to Delete</guimenu> list, because
    otherwise the added software will not work.
   </para>
  </note>
<!--just a note, podle P. Němce:
    rozdíl mezi ignored software a packages to delete:
    - packages to delete : balíky jsou natvrdo smazány
    - ignored software: pouze odstraní z patternů, ale pokud je potřeba kvůli
    závislostem, normálně se nainstaluje. Taktéž se normálně instaluje, pokud
    je zároveň 
   -->
  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Description</guimenu> tab, enter information about the
   <guimenu>Author</guimenu> of the image including <guimenu>Contact</guimenu>
   information and image <guimenu>Specification</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab, create users that need to be available
   in the target system. For each user, specify <guimenu>Login Name</guimenu>,
   <guimenu>Full Name</guimenu>, <guimenu>Password</guimenu>, <guimenu>Home
   Directory</guimenu> and <guimenu>UID</guimenu>. In <guimenu>Group
   Name</guimenu> and <guimenu>GID</guimenu>, specify the group to which the
   users belong.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Conflicting User Groups</title>
   <para>
    If the GID of any user group specified in this dialog conflicts with a GID
    of any group created by selected packages in post-installation scripts,
    image building will fail. In such a case, use different GIDs.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   In the <guimenu>Scripts</guimenu> tab, you can adjust configuration scripts
   that are used to build the image.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Directories</guimenu> tab contains two tables. In the
   <guimenu>Directory with System Configuration</guimenu> table, you can
   specify directories to copy to the root directory of the resulting system.
   For example, add a directory with configuration files. In the second table,
   <guimenu>Directory with Scripts</guimenu>, add scripts to the
   <filename>config</filename> directory to run after the installation of all
   the image packages.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
