<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.slepos_boot_64_images">
 <title>Booting 64-Bit Client Images</title>
 <para>
   Branches that only use either 64-bit or 32-bit images require no additional
  configuration.
</para>
<para>Mixed branches are configured as described in <xref linkend="sec.adminserv.newkernel"/>.</para>

<para>The default <systemitem>scDistributionContainer</systemitem> LDAP object is used for the first boot of terminals with undetermined architecture. This object must contain the 32-bit &sle; 11 kernel that can be booted on both 32-bit and 64-bit clients.</para>

<para>If the terminal fails to boot the default 32-bit &sle; 11-based image, the initial boot can be done via USB using a special image (see <xref linkend="sec.kiwi.wireless"/> for further info):</para>

<screen>cd /var/lib/SLEPOS/system/images/jeos-5.0.0 
kiwi --bootusb initrd-netboot-suse-SLES12.x86_64-2.1.1.splash.gz</screen>

<para>Alternatively, it is possible to manually create an <systemitem>scWorkstation</systemitem> object in the LDAP database prior to the first boot. The <systemitem>scWorkstation</systemitem> entry must point to the 64-bit &sle; 12-based image in the custom <systemitem>scDistributionContainer</systemitem> LDAP object.</para>

<para>The boot process with the custom <systemitem>scDistributionContainer</systemitem> LDAP object consists of the following steps:</para>

<procedure>
<step>
<para>
The terminal boots the 32-bit &sle; 11-based boot image.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
The terminal is registered. This creates the <systemitem>scWorkstation</systemitem> object in the LDAP database and the <systemitem>config.<replaceable>MAC</replaceable></systemitem> file.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
The generated <systemitem>config.<replaceable>MAC</replaceable></systemitem> file points to the 64-bit &sle; 12-based image in the custom <systemitem>scDistributionContainer</systemitem> LDAP object.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
The system image is downloaded.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Kernel parameters (including version) are compared, and the terminal is then rebooted. If the <systemitem>/srv/SLEPOS</systemitem> service partition is configured, the new boot image is started via Kexec.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
The client boots the 64-bit &sle; 12-based boot image.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
The &sle; 12-based system image is activated and booted.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<sect2 xml:id="cha.slepos_boot_troubleshoot">
<title>Dealing with Boot-Related Issues</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Problem: &pos; terminal fails to boot the default kernel</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Solution: The terminal must be configured to use specific kernel before the first boot. To do this, create a USB boot image with the correct kernel as shown in the following example:
</para>

<screen>cd /var/lib/SLEPOS/system/images/jeos-5.0.0
kiwi --bootusb initrd-netboot-suse-SLES12.x86_64-2.1.1.splash.gz</screen>

<para>
Use then the created image for the initial boot of the terminal. For further information about creating a boot image, refer to <xref linkend="sec.kiwi.wireless"/>.
</para>

<para>In cases when the MAC and hwtype properties of the terminal are known and external DHCP is not used, you can use the following command to prepare a MAC-specific PXE configuration that points to terminal-specific kernel and initrd:</para>

<screen>echo "HWTYPE=<replaceable>&lt;string&gt;</replaceable>" > /srv/tftpboot/upload/hwtype.<replaceable>MAC</replaceable>.<replaceable>HASH</replaceable></screen>

<para>
The <replaceable>&lt;string&gt;</replaceable> refers to the machine name as reported by BIOS (for example, IBM4852526). The optional <replaceable>HASH</replaceable> value is used to prevent file conflicts (see <xref linkend="ad_cntrlhw"/>). Since no conflicts should occur before the initial registration, the <replaceable>HASH</replaceable> value can be omitted:
</para>

<screen>echo "HWTYPE=<replaceable>&lt;string&gt;</replaceable>" > /srv/tftpboot/upload/hwtype.<replaceable>MAC</replaceable></screen>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>Problem: Booting the &pos; client fails with the "vga=0x314 option is deprecated" error message</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Solution: For &sle; 12-based branches, remove the <systemitem>vga=0x314</systemitem> kernel parameter from the <systemitem>posdefaults</systemitem> object in the LDAP database using the <systemitem>posAdmin</systemitem> tool. For mixed branches, remove the <systemitem>vga=0x314</systemitem> kernel parameter from the <systemitem>posdefaults</systemitem> object and add the parameter to each &sle; 11-based boot image via the <systemitem>scDistributionContainer</systemitem> object.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>
</sect1>
